<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The day dawned both to Jews and Gentiles, and clear discoveries of light and righteousness; the bright and moning star appearing Jacob wrestled with the angel until the break of the day, and would not let him go until he blessed him.</title>
            <author>D. W. (Dorothy White)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65725</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222571</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833727</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833727</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38205</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65725)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38205)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2221:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The day dawned both to Jews and Gentiles, and clear discoveries of light and righteousness; the bright and moning star appearing Jacob wrestled with the angel until the break of the day, and would not let him go until he blessed him.</title>
                  <author>D. W. (Dorothy White)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, 9-16   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Dorothy Wight [i.e. White].</note>
                  <note>With errata at foot of p. 16.</note>
                  <note>Text and register are continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Copy trimmed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Swarthmore College Library, Pennsylvania.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38205:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Day DAWNED BOTH TO JEWS AND GENTILES, And Clear Diſcoveries of LIGHT AND Righteouſneſs; The Bright and Morning STAR Appearing.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Jacob</hi> wreſtled with the Angel until the breaks of the day, and would not let him go until he bleſſed him.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year. 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:38205:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38205:2"/>
            <head>The Day dawned both to Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and clear diſcoveries of Light and Righteouſneſs.</head>
            <p>IN the Beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God, and the ſame was with him in the Beginning; by it was all things made that was made, and without it was nothing made that was made: ſo without him their is nothing can be made: as he ſaid without me ye can do nothing, ſo then it is by Grace in Jeſus Chriſt that Salvation cometh; for by Grace are ye ſaved, as he ſaith unto <hi>Paul,</hi> My Grace is ſufficient for thee; ſo Grace and Truth came by Jeſus Chriſt the Lord of Glory, in whom all Glory endeth, unto whom all Glory is returned and aſcribed, unto him who ſi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teth upon the Throne, who liveth for ever, before whom the four and twenty Elders and Beaſt fell down and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped God, ſaying, Worthy, worthy is the Lord God and the Lamb, and to receive all Power, Honour, Glory, Might, Majeſty, and Dominion be given unto him that liveth for ever and for ever more: not unto us beauſe we can do nothing, but all honour unto him becauſe he can do all things, who created all things by the Word of his Power, which word breathed into Man the breath of Life, in the beginning, and the word is Life, and in it is the Light of Men, and the Light is perfect, and cometh from above from the Father of Lights, and as the Father hath Life in himſelf, ſo he hath given the Son to have life in himſelf; and whoſoever believe in the Son, hath Eternal
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38205:3"/>Life in him, and he that hath not the Son hath not Life, but I am come that ye may have Life, and that ye may have it more abundantly, that your joy may be full, that ye may know Life and Immortality brought to light. By him that is true, is the perfection of Beauty, who is the Glory of all Nations, unto him ſhall the gathering of all Nations be, that they may ſee him in his ſhinings, of whom the Prophets have foretold, and behold, it is now come to paſs, his coming was propheſied of, that he ſhould come in, and with his thouſands and ten thouſands, with his innumerably companies and Troups and Armies of Saints and Angels, and the Armies that are in Heaven fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, who rideth on his White Horſe, whoſe face is as lightning, and his Raiment as white as Snow, who hath a Rainbow about his Head, and now he is come to Reign, and to ſit on the Throne; he that was dead is now alive, he lives for evermore; he that ſaith, Behold, I come quickly, and I will not tarry; and for the cry of the Poor, and the ſighing of the needy, I wil ariſe, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, I have heard, I have heard the cries of my Afflicted, I have heard, I have heard the groaning of the oppreſſed, and I am coming down to deliver, becauſe the cries of <hi>Sion</hi> as unto me the cries of the travelling ones, whoſe pains ſhall haſten, deliver; and becauſe this is her cry, How long Lord holy and true art thou, ariſe and avenge our cauſe on them that dwell on the Earth, alſo this was the cry of the ſlain that lay under the Altar, that was ſlain, and filled all the day long, theſe had the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Jeſus, theſe were beheaded for it, theſe had no other head but Chriſt, theſe were hidden in him, and he was head over them, and all that did Reign as head over them were taken away; So Chriſt in them was the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority, he Reigned King in his Kingdom, where the Kingdoms of the World are become the Kingdom of God; and his Chriſt, and he is become all and all in them: Theſe are the true Spouſe that is coming up out
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38205:3"/>of the Wilderneſs, leaning upon the breaſt of her beloved, and indeed there is no other to be leaned upon beſides him, upon whom help is laid, he hath laid help on him that is mighty, and whither ſhall we go but unto him, Thou haſt the word of Eternal life, the word of life and peace, that ſatisfieth the diſquieted Soul, for it is he that diſſolves the doubts by the ſweet incomes of his love, and ſweet diſtilling Showers from above, by his former and latter Rain, and bleſſed are all they that feel and enjoy it, yea, moſt of all happy and crowned for ever ſhall they be that dwell in his love. O what ſhall I ſay, there is not greater love, more enduring love, more conſtraining love, confirming love, it confirms and eſtabliſheth that heart that feels it; they can ſay, O God my heart is fixed in thee and upon thee not in the form but in the power of God; ſuch are fixed Stars, fixed in the Firmament of God's power, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Stars, ſome greater and ſome leſſer, every one in its Degree and Order, the wiſe Creator hath fixed them in the Firmament of his glorious power, ſuch come to ſhine above the Word, above the dark forms of the World, in the Firmament of the Heavens in Paradiſe. Again, where God hath Planted them, as in that day wherein the Morning Stars did ſing together, and the Sons of God ſhouted for joy, there was a mutual harmony, an Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal harmony, an innocent harmony, all muſt be brought unto this into Innocency, into Joy and Humility; as the Angels in Heaven, ſo God will make up his Church of ſuch Jewels, as he will compleat and bind them up in the bond of Peace and covenant of Love, out of all ſtrife, he will redeem them, and from amongſt men. And the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs number which <hi>John</hi> ſaw on Mount <hi>Sion</hi> of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Kindreds, Tongues, and People which were to be brought there, which God is bringing to paſs in this our day; yea, of all Nations, and of all ſorts, of People the Lord is now gathering, as a Shepherd gathers his Sheep together and brings them to their Fold; ſo is Chriſt the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38205:4"/>true Shepherd, bringing all the true Jews to the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> from above, not onely into one form, but into the heavenly power, and heavenly life of Jeſus where they ſhall ſing Hallelujah with the Lord God, and the Lamb, who hath redeemed them, and ſuch as are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by his power, and waſhed by the word of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, who are made white in the Bloud of the Lamb, who are come to the Bloud of Sprinkling, and to know their Conſcience waſhed from dead works, theſe come again to ſerve the living God, and worſhip him in the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of holineſs in the light of Righteouſneſs; into it muſt the Nations be gathered, the Nations of them that are ſaved, muſt walk in the light of the Lord, and of the Lamb in the Light of the Holy City, in the Light of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Lord is gathering all Nations in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one place of Worſhip, into his own Spirit, the Spirit of Truth as he ſaith, ſuch Worſhippers is my Father, ſeeking to worſhip him; and in the beginning of the firſt creation, he ſaid, Let the Waters be gathered into one place; ſo the people are the Waters which are to be gathered into one place of Worſhip. And <hi>John</hi> ſaw the numberly number that ſtood upon Mount <hi>Sion</hi> of all Nations, and he ſaith, I heard the ſound of many Waters, as of a great people with Harps, harping with their harps, and they ſung a new ſong which none could learn, but they that followed he Lamb; theſe were the redeemed of God which were brought home, theſe ſung before his Throne, who lived for, ever, who had their Names written in Heaven, theſe Reigned with the Lamb over the Beaſt, and over his power, theſe were ſealed with the Seal of God in their foreheads, and in their right hand they ſtood upon the Sea of Glaſs mingled with fire; and <hi>John</hi> ſaid, I hear as it were the ſound of a Trumpet, it talking with me; ſo all the redemed comes to hear as well as <hi>John</hi> the ſound of the Trumpet, it of God ſounding from heaven in them; that Trumpet ſounded clearer and clearer, which is the way of the Bridegroom
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38205:4"/>talking with them who are his true Spouſe, as a man talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with his friend: So they come to the Miniſtration of the Spirit, unto the miniſtration of Angels; he ſaith, Come let us reaſon together, and <hi>Abraham</hi> reaſoned with the Lord, and convened with the Lord, unto whoſe houſe the Angels came; and the Lord ſaith, ſhall I do any thing and hide it from my ſervant <hi>Abraham:</hi> ſo all that truly ſerve the Lord and fear the Lord, they are of the faithful Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſhall be accounted to the Lord for a Generation; yea, his Seed ſhall ſerve him, the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Seed unto whom the promiſe is ſo, they ſhall be a numberleſs number that ſhall come from the four Winds of the Earth, and haſten to the Holy City, whoſe Gates are not ſhop by day nor by night, but yet the unclean can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter therein, none but the redeemed, the waſhed and purified by the Spirit of Judgment, and burning them that do paſs through the Rivers of Judgment, that do paſs through <hi>Jordan,</hi> ſuch enter the good Land, and know Judgment brought forth into Victory, ſo the Lamb and the Lyon comes to lie down together, and the little child ſhall lead them; ſo they come to be lead by Chriſt their leader, they are little children in Chriſt, he that would be greateſt amongſt his Diſciples, muſt become as this little child, as Chriſt himſelf ſaith, ſo they muſt be led by him as thoſe little children that cannot go of themſelves, nor are not able to do any thing without him, as he ſaith unto <hi>Peter,</hi> Once thou girdeſt thy ſelf, and wenteſt whither thou wouldeſt, but another ſhall gird thee, and thou ſhalt be led whither thou would not, ſo he leads his into a dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly croſs and ſelf-denial; Chriſt ſaith, if any man will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after me, and be my Diſciple, he muſt firſt deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and take up his daily croſs, and follow me; a croſs to the carnal mind, which ſtands in death and enmity to the pure appearance of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. So to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally minded is death, but to be Spiritually minded is life and peac; Sow to the Spirit that you may reap life; for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38205:5"/>if ye ſow to the fleſh you will reap the wages of ſin and death; but all that come to the gift of God, which is Life and Truth, and receive it in the love of it, they come to be ſet free by it, and if the Truth ſet you free, then are you free indeed, no more children of the Bondwoman, but of the Freewoman, which brings forth the Heir of life, the Son of Righteouſneſs, which ſhe comes to be clothed with, and to have the Moon under her Feet, ſhe is clothed with his Righteouſneſs, with the Righteouſneſs of Faith, which ſpeaketh on this wiſe, Juſtification by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Abraham</hi> by Faith was juſtified, and his Faith was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs: ſo every one that is a child of Faith, they are of <hi>Abraham's</hi> ſeed, according to promiſe, they feel their Faith ſpeaking to them better things than the bloud of <hi>Abel,</hi> ſo they grow up in Faith, and from Faith to Faith, and from ſtrength to ſtrength, and ſo at laſt they meet with the Lord in <hi>Sion,</hi> where they behold the King in his beauty; and theſe come to ſay, How beautiful are thy Tents O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> how excellent are the dwellings of <hi>Jacobs O Iſrael?</hi> who is like to thee a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſaved of the Lord; and this ſhall be the Song that ſhall be heard in the Land of <hi>Judea;</hi> we have a ſtrong City for which God hath appointed ſalvation for Walls and for Bulworks, a City that hath foundations whoſe Builder and Maker is God.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The God of <hi>Abraham</hi> and of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hath cauſed us in pleaſant Tents to dwell.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> was perfect, he was in his Tent</l>
               <l>when the Angel to him God then had ſent.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> a plain man dwelt in Tents,</l>
               <l>Therefore O <hi>Iſrael</hi> haſten in within thy Tent,</l>
               <l>And ſtand within thy Tent door that the Angels</l>
               <l>of God thou mayeſt ſee come in unto thee,</l>
               <l>When they do glad tidings brings</l>
               <l>That thou may'ſt Hallelujah ſing, for evermore.</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:38205:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l> For ſuch redemption is drawing nigh,</l>
               <l>That the redeemed ſhall ſing on high;</l>
               <l>Yea their peace ſhall ſo increaſe,</l>
               <l>They ſhall make ſweet melody.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So turn into your ſtrong hold ye Priſoners of hope, hold faſt your Hope, Faith, and Confidence, which Anchors go in him that is the Rock, which the Storms ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did nor never can, nor never ſhall more, that it may be known you are the mans building, that the Rain nor Storms could not beat down, becauſe it was grounded upon the Rock; then you will come to ſay, and experience, that Greater is he that is in you, than he that is without you, or he that is in the World; ſo the Prince of this World cometh to try and to ſift your Building, but all that are anchored in the Rock in Chriſt Jeſus, who did conquer and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and was made perfect through ſuffering ſo all that are in him, ſhall be made more than Conquerours, through his love; this is their victory, even their Faith, by which they overcome the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; ſo by Faith <hi>Noah</hi> entred into the Ark, which by Faith he had built: ſo all ye that have built this day, the Ark of God's. Covenant by Faith, and are entred into it, will have a ſafe hiding place within the rock, an hiding place, which is ſure for ever; and all who are without this, who are not ſo ſurely builded, the Flouds is coming that will waſh them away, and quite beat down their building, ſuch will be ſeen to be the fooliſh builders, whoſe houſe is upon the ſands, where no foundation can be laid, and bleſſed is that man whoſe God is the Lord this day that comes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and to ſay, O the height and the depth, the length and the breadth of the love of God which we have in Chriſt Jeſus, that unſeparable love, that ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abounding love, that far exceeds the love of Women, of which I am perſwaded, neither Principalities nor Powers, things paſt, things preſent, nor that which is to come, will be able to ſeparate thoſe from this love of God, which they have in Chriſt Jeſus, who are firmly fixed therein, as the Sun in the firmament, by a perpetual decree, ſo do the fixed Stars ſtand upheld by the Lords right hand, theſe are the true Spouſe, that leans on her beloveds breaſt; he doth her Aid and Aſſiſt, he nouriſhed her in the Wilderneſs, for in times, time, and half a time, until the Floud and Storm is over and the Man-child, the Whale is caſt up unto God, and into his Throne, ſo he that overcometh will I give to ſit in my Throne, as I overcome and ſit in my Fathers Throne, ſo he that overcometh hath right to eat of the Tree of Life; he that doth the commandment of Jeſus, he overcometh he entreth into the Gates of the holy City, whoſe Gates are filled with praiſes and everlaſting Hallelujahs, which all the Redeemed ſhall ſing for ever, who doth know the overcoming in them. Come up thou North wind and blow, and thou Eaſt wind and blow, and South and Weſt wind and blow upon the Garden, and kindle the Spices thereof, that the frequent ſmell of the ſweet Spices may go forth, that when the beloved comes to walk there in his Garden, he may take delight in the ſweet favour thereof, that it may be as the ſavour of <hi>Jacob,</hi> as of the field which the Lord hath bleſſed, the ſweet breath of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and breathing forth of life: my beloved is become as a Fountain of Gardens, and ſweet diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhowers, always diſtilling and dropping the ſweet heavenly ſhowers, my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved is become as a bed of ſweet Spices, and as the dew of <hi>Hermon</hi> diſtilling and running down as the ſweet Odours and precious Oyntment, he is altogether lovely, he is the chief of ten thouſand, his doctrine drops as the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38205:6"/>dew, and as the ſweet ſhowers in the Summer ſpring, which cauſeth the Lilies to grow; and the Turtle doth ſing in the ſweet vallies where the Rivers of God's pleaſure doth flow.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The Wilderneſs ſhall become as a pleaſant Spring,</l>
               <l>The Deſert forth her pleaſant fruits ſhall bring.</l>
               <l>And the faithful ſhall both rejoyce and ſing.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And now my beloved friends, I ſhall ſhew you a more excellent way, a way which the Lord hath caſt up, a high and a glorious way, a way for the ranſomed and the redeemed to walk in, a way that the wayfaring man, though a fool, ſhall not err therein, the way which is Chriſt, the new and living way, and the good old way ſo as many as hath received Chriſt, ſo let them walk in him, and he is the way that is new caſt up, for the Gentiles to walk in, the way, the truth, and the life, and no man cometh to the Father but by me, ſaith Chriſt, and no man cometh to me but he whom the Father draweth, ſo all muſt come to the feeling of the drawings of the Father in them, who draws them to the Son, that they may know the Son lifted up in them, who will then draw all men after him, ſo as the outward Sun draws up by the heat and vertue thereof, and by its ſhining, all the Trees and Fruits of the Earth, ſo the inward Sun, the Sun of Righteouſneſs, it draws up all the Trees of Righteouſneſs after him: Ye are the Trees of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, the planting of the Lord, and he ſhall grow up as a young Plant, and as a Tree by the Rivers of Water, whoſe leaf ſhall never fail, but always ſhall proſper, they ſhall be as green Olive-branches round about his table. And <hi>Joſeph</hi> was as a fruitful bow growing by a Well ſide, whoſe branches did ſpread over the wall, over the wall of Separation, his ſheaf came to overtop all the other; though the Archers ſhot at him,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Yet <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Bow abode in ſtrength,</l>
               <l>And he got the victory at length;</l>
               <l>And how the famine got into their land,</l>
               <l>They were not aware, neither did they underſtand.</l>
               <l>But at laſt when they came to ſee.</l>
               <l>Then to <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſubmit muſt they.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And now Oh my beloved friends, you that have the living taſt and ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of life, eat and drink abundantly, for the more you taſt, the more you will deſire, it is deſirable meat it is meat indeed, as Chriſt ſaith, My fleſh is meat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and my bloud is drink indeed, and except ye eat my fleſh and drink my bloud you have no life in you. Theſe were hard ſayings to be underſtood, about which their minds fell a reaſoning: Can this man give us his fleſh to eat, reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> who came to Jeſus by night, reaſoning with fleſh and bloud, which ſtands in the darkneſs; but fleſh and bloud never revealed theſe things, but he that is born of the Spirit comes to ſee theſe things revealed by the Spirit of Chriſt the Lord; and as the Wind bloweth where it liſteth, ſo the Spirit deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from heaven like a Dove; and behold, ſaith the true Spouſe, My beloved hath Doves eyes, ſo they that were waiting at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for the promiſe of his coming the ſecond time, he came and appeared in the midſt of them, as he faith I will be in the mid<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of them, he aſcended upon them, when the doors were ſhut, as a mighty ruſhing Wind ſo fell the Holy upon them, which ſat upon each man like a Dove, they then came to ſpeak wich new tongues the wonderfull things of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38205:6"/>God which they had ſeen, and theſe things are now ſeen by his deſcending again from Heaven as lightning, and as die lightning cometh cut of the eaſt, and ſhineth into the weſt, ſo ſhall the coming of the Son of Man the ſecond time without ſin to ſalvation, and we have ſeen his coming and the enlightning Angels of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is coming to enlighten the whole earth, according to his ancient promiſe, it is now coming to paſs, the glory and knowledge of the Lord ſhall fill and cover the earth, as the waters fill and cover the ſea, ſo it is the ſpiritual bread and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual wine that the outward fleſh and bloud ſignifies; the inward and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Grace, the inward ſpiritual bread, which ail his Diſciples did, and do ſeed on, as they ſaid evermore, Give us this bread; and, I am the bread of life, ſaid Chriſt, and whoſoever eateth thereof, they ſhall never hunger again, and whoſoever ſhall drink of the waters that I ſhall give, they ſhall never hunger again, and but it ſhall be in them a well of waters ſpringing up unto everlaſting life; theſe are the pleaſant waters, the waters of <hi>Shiloh,</hi> which runn ſoftly, ſweetly, and pleaſantly, as the honey out of the rock, ſo is the ſpringing in of the word of life more ſweeter than the honey and the honey-comb, this is the new Wine of the Kingdom, the fruits of the heavenly wine which the ſaithfull drink of every day, new in the Fathers kingdom, and this is the cup of Bleſſing, this is the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Bread and Wine, this is the ſpiritual Supper of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and this all are to eat of, untill the Lord come in them.</p>
            <p>The outward Supper was but a Figure and a Sign of the inward and Spiritual Grace, ſo the inward Spiritual Grace and Heavenly Bread, is that which the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward figured out, ſo great is the Myſtery of Godlineſs; Chriſt manifeſteth in mortal fleſh, and theſe things hath the Lord in his wiſdom hid from the wiſe, and the prudent of this world; and he hath revealed them unto Babes and ſucklings, even to new born Babes, that are new born. Again, they that deſire the ſincere milk of the Word that they may grow thereby, but many prophets and wiſe men deſired to ſee theſe things, but they did not ſee them therefore, the world by its wiſdom never came to know God, but he that will be truly wiſe in the things that are of God, muſt firſt become a fool as to tthe Worlds wiſdom, and come to a Child-like ſtate; My little Children, ſaith the faithfull and true, for whom I again travel in birth until Chriſt be formed in you.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The figleav'd garment though ſewed with a ſeam,</l>
               <l>It ſhall not ſerve to cover the unclean,</l>
               <l>But their nakedneſs this day will be ſeen;</l>
               <l>The people walk in clouds and forms,</l>
               <l>They do not ſeee clear light,</l>
               <l>But the day draws near, he will appear,</l>
               <l>And he will ſhine moſt bright.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Lord of Hoſts is coming into the Vineyard this day, and to look over it, and to look for the fruits thereof, and behold, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, I planted my Vineyard upon a very fruitfull Mountain, I digged a well therein, and made a a Wine-preſs therein, I alſo made a Tower therein, all this have I done; what more could the Lord of Hoſts have done that he hath not done for his Vineyard: but he cometh to look for fruit there, but behold wild Grapes, Grapes ſome of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt;</hi> therefore thus ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the Lord of Hoſts, Repent and return, and work your firſt works, elſe, Behold I come quickly and lay the Vineyard deſolate, and take away the Hedge that was about it, and let in the Beaſts of prey upon it; I wil alſo forbid the clouds that they ſhall not tain upon it. And this is the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38205:7"/>mentation that may be taken up over a great part of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who doth bound in their pride as well as other iniquities, by which the truth of God comes greatly to ſuffer by their unrighteous walking, who profeſs the Light and walk in darkneſs; which cauſeth the people to ſay, All are alike, but we ſay, No, the workers of Iniquity muſt bear their burden, but the children of the Light, and of the day of God, they will be clear of the works of Iniquity, and of the workers thereof: The day of ſeparation is coming, although the Seed of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as the ſand on the Sea-ſhore, yet but a remnant of them ſhall be ſaved: and let not any think the worſe of the precious truth, becauſe of the ill carriages of ſome, and the debauchery of ſome becauſe of the breaking out of the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r corruption, who never were well wounded, nor never came to the ſound healing, but tins was the complaint of the daughter of Sion, her wounds were ſlightly healed, therefore all come to the ſearch, how haſt thou been wounded; have the Dragon had ſuch a wound in his head that he can never be healed more: he that will wound the Dragon is come and ſlay Ahab: yea, the Angels hand is laying hold of the Dragon, the old Serpent called the Devil, and all his pride and iniquities ſhall be ſlain with him, the Lord will ſearch the camp, and all ſhall ſee what hinders them, what Golden wedge is hidden in it, and every one muſt caſt lots, and chuſe to himſelf: Is it, I; Is it, I; What ſleeper is there for which cauſe the waves thus beat? read within what is hidden within the Veſſel, is there not a ſleeper, if there be, ariſe and awake, it is high time, the God of Heaven is coming to make known who are his own, and what is his own, and what is not he will caſt out: the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God is like a net, that brought up the Fiſh both good and bad; but in the day when he gathereth them into Veſſels, he ſhall caſt the bad into the Sea again; every particular will then be concerned: Is it, I; Is it, I; am I a wiſe Virgin, have I oyl in my lamp, and is my lamp made ready, and is it burning, for the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night crie is gone forth, behold the Bridegroom cometh, every one is concerned for himſelf; ſeeing my oyl will not ſerve another, nor anothers for me, what doth the witneſs of God ſay, every one muſt feel this, the Spirit of Jeſus to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him, and this is the peace that none can give nor take away, ſo every one muſt be reconciled unto God through Jeſus Chriſt the reconciler, who came to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile the World unto himſelf, ſo all muſt follow him that reconciler that reconciles, the Lamb of God that taketh away the ſins of the World, he maketh perfect as pertaining to the conſcience, this is the perfect law of God, the covenant which is ſure; ſo there is perfection in the light of the Lord God and of the Lamb, and he perfect ail that are ſanctified, and all the works of God are perfect, and there are all compleat in him, ſo all muſt follow the Lord and his leadings, and direct guidings,, who goeth ſafely on as the meaſure of grace, as he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and believed in, ſo they will come to walk by faith which they have in them ſelves, this is the word of ſaith which was once delivered unto the Saints, which word we alſo preach to the world, and to this word the Apoſtle recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends every one unto the word of his grace, which is able to ſave them, lead them, guide them, and direct them, and build them up in the moſt holy faith, and I can ſay no other thing hut direct all unto the word of faith, unto the faithful witneſs in their own conſcience, and there to look and wait for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance and coming more and more of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, therefore haſten Lord Jeſus and come quickly.</p>
            <p>And bleſſed is he, who is found this day having on his Wedding Garment; for when the King came and beheld his gueſts, when they were come into the Bride Chamber, he looked over them; he there <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> on who had not on his Wedding Garment, he ſaid friend, How cameſt thou hither, having not on the Wedding
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38205:7"/>Garment? How many this day are got under the profeſſion pretended Friend, as he ſaith? How cameſt thou hither? Haſt thou put off the Old Man with his deeds, and put on the New Man which is Chriſt, as he ſaith? Put on the Lord Jeſus and be cloathed with him. But how is the Wedding Garment put on? Art thou cloathed with the Day Stars of God, with the everlaſting Righteouſneſs with the Righteouſneſs of Saints? put on changing of Raiment the pure and white linnen, the Garment that's waſhed of the Lamb; which muſt be without Spot, or Stain, or Blemiſh, or any ſuch thing. So muſt be every member that belong to the glorious Body of Chriſt, for as he is ſo are his members all compleat in him, this is the ſpouſe the Lambs wife, the Bride that hath made her ſelf ready waſhed and made white in his Blood: ſhining in his glory and in the beauty of Holineſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Spot, or Stain, or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing; theſe are as ſheep come up from the waſhing made pure and white in the blood of the Lamb, theſe have paſſed through Death, and ſuch he will crown with life and dominion over Death and Hell. They ſhall raign and know the thouſand years Sabbath, the Sabbath of reſt; as it is ſaid they ſhall raign with him a thouſand years and for ever and ever laſting; ſo bleſſed is he and they that hath a part in the firſt Reſurrection, on whom the ſecond Death ſhall have no power, and I am the Reſurrection and the life ſaid Chriſt, and he that believeth in me, ſaid Chriſt, ſhall never die nor ſee Death. And I will raise him in the last day, he muſt be raiſed in the day in the Light of the Lord which is day, Chriſt is the light, they muſt ariſe in him; I in them, and thet in me, and he that is in Chriſt is a new Ceature. All old things are paſſed away and all things become new; and he that hath Chriſt hath crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the fleſh with the luſt and affections thereof; ſo they come to be crucified to the World, and the World to them: ſo they come to leave their grave clothing behind fallen <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion, the ſinful luſt of die fleſh, and pride of the world, and pomps and vanities thereof, that which people have been long a talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of; but leaving thoſe things undone which they ſhould have done: but the Lord is coming to face die Nations whoſe face is in his hand, and to make known the ſayer from the doer, but it is he that doth his will ſhall be juſtified in that day, wherein he will make up his Jewels and him will he ſpare as a man ſpareth his only Son that ſerveth him, he that doth my commandments he is my Diſciple, ye are my Diſciples if ye do all whatſoever I command you.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The harlot like the ture Spouſe doth her ſelf adreſs,</l>
               <l>She ſtands up perfection, ſhe doth profeſs,</l>
               <l>But God is come and coming, her to diſcover</l>
               <l>She ſhall be ſeen before the day is over.</l>
               <l>Although ſhe ſits and rules much like a Queen,</l>
               <l>The day is coming, wherein ſhe ſhall be ſeen;</l>
               <l>And all fleſh hath ſinned and come ſhort of the glory of God,</l>
               <l>And all fleſh had corruped the way before the Lord:</l>
               <l>And alt hath been Children of wrath, and we as well as others</l>
               <l>Ye all hath been born blind from the Mother <hi>Eve.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Until the Lord Jeſus Chriſt Anointed the Eyes of the Blind, with the ointment of his own making, or eye Salve: by which he hath done the cure as he did to the Blind Man, who was born blind; and when he was asked how he came to ſee, his anſwer was this one thing. I know whereas I was once blind, I now ſee, although the mighty and the learned could not believe, ſaying, How could this Man do theſe Works he being a Sinner? thus they condemn the Juſt one; and it is ſaid, he could work no Maircles in his own Country for their unbelief ſake; ſo they that do believe can now ſay with the Blind Man, whereas I was once blind I now ſee, and this I know is the Maircles he is now a working and a doing, that t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Nations may ſee and be ſaved. And every eye ſhall ſee him,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38205:8"/>and the powers of Heaven ſhall move, then ſhall they ſee his coming in the Clouds of Heaven with power and with great Glory; and we have more than a cloud of Witneſſes who have ſeen his coming in them: ſo theſe are clouds who have the Rain in them, and the wells who have water in them, ſo many as have reſerved the ſpirit of Chriſt are the clouds in which Chriſt raineth, not the outward clouds ſeeing he faith we have more then a cloud of witneſſes, but in men he is coming to raign yea in thouſands and ten thouſands, theſe are the Armies which are in Heaven that follow the Lamb, theſe are the numberleſs number which no man could number, and <hi>John</hi> inquired of the Angel what are theſe, and he ſaid, theſe are them that have paſſed through great tribulation, whoſe garments are made white in the blood of the Lamb and they follow the Lamb which way ever he goeth; therefore they were cloathed in white for they were worthy, theſe Sung a new Song that none could learn, nor none never can learn but the followers.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Of the Lamb it is a new Song indeed,</l>
               <l>That none can ſing but the holy Seed</l>
               <l>That through death comes to be freed.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And have they not all heard, ye verily his ſound is gone forth into all Lands, and his words to the end of the Earth; ſo they heave all hard but they have not all obeyed. If ye here and obay then it ſhall go well with <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou, its the willing and obedient that ſhall eat the good of the Land, but the diſobedient mail dwell in a dry Land they ſhall be like the heath in the deſart that ſhall not know when good cometh, therefore obedience is better then ſacrifice, and to hearken is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the fat of Ramms. Therefore hear that your ſouls may live, hear what the Spirit and the Bride ſaith, come up hither, come up to the mountain of the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and he will teach you of his ways, and ye ſhall walk in his paths in the path of peace; in which all the ranſomed of the Lord walk and all the redeemed who inhabit the holy mountain of his holineſs, where no deſtroyer can never come, therefore bleſſed are the undefiled in the way who walk in the way of holineſs, in the path of peace: which leadeth them to that eternal Joy where all the ſaints in light have their true reſt, and where they come to profeſs that year that paſſeth all underſtanding, whether hath ear heard, whether have it entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heart of Man, neither can it be conceived by any, the riches of the love of God, the treaſures of life, the fulneſs of joy, and unſpeakable glory that is laid up for all the faithful ones who came to inhabit this holy mountain wherein is the feaſt of Tabernacles, or feaſt of fat things, the wine well refined from the lees. So they that dwell in thy houſe they always will praiſe thee, they that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit thy holy Mountain, they ſhall always ſing <hi>Hallelujah</hi> with him that inhabits Eternity and dwelleth in the light, he alſo dwells with the Children of men, unto that man will I look ſaid the Lord who is of a broken heart; and a contrite Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: and trembleth at my word. So the eye of the Lord runs to and fro in the Earth, but his eye is upon the faithful that they may dwell with him, ſo he ſaith, I will walk in them and dwell in them, and they ſhall be my people and the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of God is with men, and he will place his name in the midſt of them; the name of the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> in which is everlaſting ſtrength, and now the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel is flying forth, ſaying, now is Salvation come, the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ingdom of our God and the power of his Chriſt and bleſſed are they who witneſs this ſaying, the Kingdom of God. Come, in them and the day of his power come, in them which is Chriſt the power of God, theſe know the raign of Chriſt and the ſecond coming of Chriſt in the fleſh, ſo every Spirit that confeſieth that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is of God; and they that deny his coming in the fleſh, are of Antichriſt, but many will confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt once came in the fleſh, but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38205:8"/>they muſt come to know the ſecond coming of Chriſtin their fleſh, ſo than they come to a right knowledge of Chriſt in them the hope of their glory, and ſuch will come to ſay, although, I have known Jeſus Chriſt after the fleſh, I ſhall henceforth know him So no more but after the ſpirit, a quicknig Spirit, the Lord from Heaven; who is come to quicken and make alive them that were dead in ſins and treſpaſſes: ſo theſe come to know the work that Chriſt came to do in them, and and to make them alive unto God, ſo ye that were once dead in your ſins and treſpaſſes, he hath made alive; and theſe are faithful witneſſes of his coming and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection: who have ſeen his comingin them? yea Chriſt is their Wiſdom, their Sanctification, and Redemption; and they can ſay the day of the redeemed is come wherein they come up as ſheep from the waſhing, and through the waſhing of Regeneration. Theſe comes to be waſhed from all Spots and Stains, and to ware there waſhed Garments without ſpot or ſtain, theſe were the number that <hi>John</hi> ſaw they were not defiled with Women, but they were Virgins that follow the Lamb ſo was the State of the Church of Chriſt ſignified, and foreſhone by the Angel unto the faithful: and he ſaith, I ſend mine Angels to teſtifie the things to the Churches, he that walked in the midſt of the golden Candleſtick, he that is in the midſt of the Holy City; the ſtreets whereof is paved with pure gold, and he ſaith, I will make die Soul of man more precious than the golden wedg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Ophir ſo he is purifying and refining as a refiner of Silver, and a purifier of gold as ſeven times in the fire, that his workman-ſhip may ſhine forth in the Nations. And Chriſt ſaith, I come to kindle a fire in the Earth, and what if it be already kindled, but doſt thou feel a ſpark of this holy fire, that Chriſt is kindling of it in thee of his fire of Love, doſt thou feel the ſmoking flax begin to ſmoke in thy heart? And doſt thou feel the bruiſed Reed? Doſt thou feel thy heart begin to be made tender, and a deſire begin to ariſe to know the Lord? Then ſurely the Lord will not quench this ſmoking flax, tho it be but a Spark, it ſhall become a flame: and he will not break the braſed reed, but he will bring it forth to victory. So though the grace be little in appearance it is ſtrong enough, it is ſufficient to ſave all that truſt in it, it is ſaving grace, ſo though the faith be little as a grain of Muſtardſeed; it is able to remove the Mountains, and to raire the hills far away, it is like the little leeven that the Woman hid in the three meaſures of Meal, until the whole lump was levened; ſo grace is the leeven which as it works in thee, it will work ſuch a change and beget ſuch a pure mind, ſuch a Spiritual, a Chriſt like mind, ſo thou wilt become like minded and changed into his divine Nature, a natural branch ingrafted into the vine and taken of the wild Olive, and ingrafted into the new ſtock, ſo the root will be new and the fruit will be new alſo; ſo thou wilt come to know the root and of-ſpring of <hi>David,</hi> thou wilt ſpring and grow up in him who is the righteous branch of <hi>David,</hi> who ſhall ſpring forth as die Cedar of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and grow as a tree by the Rivers of water, whoſe leaf ſhall never fade this tree, ſhall grow again in Paradiſe; and ſhall bring forth twelve manner of fruits, and ſhall yield its fruit every month, and bring it forth in due ſeaſon; ſo the people of the Lord are taught of the Lord, and in righteouſneſs they come to be eſtabliſhed, and great ſhall be their peace and their peace ſhall flow as the River; they ſhall be as a well watered Garden, who feel the heavenly, bedewing and ſhowres, the former and the latter Rain, the ſhowers of his mercy which are renewed morning by morning, ſo they will come to learn the parable if the fig-tree, when ſhe began to put forth her tender bud, as in the the time of ſpring, then behold Summer draweth neigh, doth this fig-tree be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to caſt forth her buds in the doſt, thou feel the time of come in thee, is there a ſpring of life ſpringing up in the? than ſinners draweth neigh wherein the turtles
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38205:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>voice will be heard, and the ſinging of Birds will be known, and ſuch will come to ſing the Winter is paſt, the rain is over and gone.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>The Turtles voice is heard now at laſt,</l>
                  <l>The ſing of Burds is came</l>
                  <l>The Lord is come and ſecret he doth reveal</l>
                  <l>They can not hinder him by all there wit and ſtill;</l>
                  <l>But his Enemies all he will out run,</l>
                  <l>He will conquer them, he will them over come:</l>
                  <l>The voice of the Bridegroom is heard this day,</l>
                  <l>The voice of trumphet and of Victory,</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>21 5th Month, 1684.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Written for the Author, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy Wight</hi>
            </trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Victory they ſhall all know that follow the Lord fully.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. line 22. for <hi>Deliver</hi> read <hi>Deliverance.</hi> l. 26. for <hi>filled</hi> r. <hi>killed.</hi> p. 3. l. 20. for <hi>word</hi> r. <hi>world.</hi> p. 4. l 21. for <hi>numberly</hi> r. <hi>numberleſs.</hi> l. 36. for <hi>way</hi> r. <hi>voice.</hi> p. 5. l. 14. for <hi>ſhop</hi> r. <hi>ſhut.</hi> p. 9. l. 6. for <hi>go</hi> r. <hi>you.</hi> l. 7. for <hi>more</hi> r. <hi>move.</hi> l. 8. <hi>you are the Wiſe mans building.</hi> l. 33. for <hi>whale is caſt</hi> r. <hi>while caſt.</hi> l. 40. r. <hi>fragrant Garden.</hi> p. 12 l. 51. for <hi>ſaid</hi> r. <hi>ſaw.</hi> p. 13. l. 5. for <hi>Stars</hi> r. <hi>Star.</hi> l. 6. for <hi>changing</hi> r. <hi>change.</hi> l. 29. for <hi>face</hi> r. <hi>fan</hi> twice in the line. l. 41. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>its.</hi> p. 14. l. 4. for <hi>reſerved</hi> r. <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</hi> l. 30. for <hi>profeſs</hi> r. <hi>poſſeſs.</hi> ibid. for <hi>year</hi> r. <hi>peace.</hi> l. 31. for <hi>whether</hi> r. <hi>neither,</hi> twice in the line. p. 15. l. 50. r. <hi>but doſt thou feel the time of Spring come in thee.</hi> l. 51. r. <hi>is there a Spring of Life ſpringing up in the Summer.</hi> p. 16. l. 5. for <hi>ſecret</hi> r. <hi>ſecrets.</hi> l. 6. for <hi>ſtill.</hi> r. <hi>skill.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
